Guide to the Margaret B. Young papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Margaret B. Young Papers,
1921-2010
[Bulk Dates: 1965-2000].
Young, Margaret B.
12.26 linear ft. (6 record cartons, and 6 flat boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1622
9503889
History
Margaret Buckner Young was born in Campbellsville, Kentucky on March 29, 1921. After receiving her primary and secondary education in Aurora, Illinois, Young went to Kentucky State Industrial College where she graduated with majors in English and French and met Whitney M. Young, Jr. The couple married in 1944 before Whitney left for Europe to serve with the army in World War II. During Whitney’s absence, Margaret Young continued her education, earning a master’s degree in educational psychology at the University of Minnesota in 1946. Whitney joined her in Minnesota, beginning his work with the National Urban League there. In 1953 the Youngs moved to Atlanta where Whitney served as the Dean of the Atlanta School of Social Work. Margaret was a professor of educational psychology at Spelman College. During the family’s time in Atlanta, Margaret was frustrated by her inability to actively protest the dramatic segregation there without endangering her young children.
In 1961, the Youngs moved to New Rochelle, New York, and Whitney took on the role of Executive Director at the National Urban League. As her husband gained prominence, Margaret Young retained a more private role concentrating on raising their two daughters. She began a career as a writer, publishing articles including “A Negro Mother Speaks of her Challenging Role in a Changing World” for Parents’ Magazine (1964) and the Public Affairs Pamphlet “How to Bring Up Your Child Without Prejudice” (1965). She also published several children’s books including The First Book of American Negroes (1966), and The Picture Life of Martin Luther King, Jr. (1967). While Margaret Young’s writings echo her husband’s goals of racial equality, Young used her writing and her work with school children to make an independent mark on education practices in the United States regarding race, racism, and African American history.
Whitney Young drowned off the coast of Lagos, Nigeria in 1971. His death brought about abrupt changes in Margaret Young’s personal and professional life. As Whitney Young’s widow, Margaret Young dedicated herself to activism for racial equality by taking on numerous professional positions. She continued her husband’s efforts to improve relations between the United States and Africa, traveling to Nigeria alone in 1974 and again with President Jimmy Carter on a state visit in 1978. She served in the United Nations as a member of the United States delegation to the 28th General Assembly in Yugoslavia in 1974. There she presented a paper on “The Promotion and Protection of Human Rights of National, Ethnic and Other Minorities.” Young also was a member of a panel for the United Nations Association of the United States of America considering United States relations with China in 1978 and 1979. In the 1980s she served lengthy terms on the boards of directors at several corporations including Philip Morris and New York Life. Her work in these positions reflected her ongoing dedication to achieving racial equality, but she also gained experience and recognition beyond her input on racial issues.
Margaret Young was also deeply involved in the commemoration of her husband as the head of the Whitney M. Young, Jr. Memorial Foundation and through her involvement with the National Urban League. She also worked with many other institutions that sought to preserve the memory of Whitney Young including Columbia University, Kentucky State University, the Clark Atlanta School of Social Work, and the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania.
In 1990, Margaret Young moved to Denver, Colorado and dissolved the Whitney M. Young, Jr. Memorial Foundation. In her retirement she continued to write stories for children that featured African American characters. She died at age eighty-eight on December 5, 2009 of complications from cancer.
Scope and Content
This collection is made up of Margaret Young's professional papers, writings, personal and professional correspondence, biographical material, and photographs. A significant portion of the material, including a number of photographs, documents the career and commemoration of Whitney M. Young, Jr. There are several oversized items including photo albums, awards, and scrapbooks that relate to Margaret Young's professional activities and travels. The files span Margaret Young's lifetime, but most of the material documents her activities after Whitney Young's death in 1971.
Arrangement
Material is arranged into 7 series
Series I: Whitney M. Young, Jr. Files, 1921-2009
Series II: Professional Activities, 1964-1996
Series III: Writings and Publications, 1953-1997
Series IV: Correspondence, 1945-2009
Series V: Personal Papers, 1921-2010
Series VI: Photographs, 1930s-2003
Subseries VI.1: Margaret Young Photographs, 1930s-2003
Subseries VI.2: Whitney M. Young, Jr. Photographs, 1943-1996
Series VII: Awards and Recognition, 1971-1993
Subjects
National Urban League.; Philip Morris USA.; United Nations.; Whitney M. Young, Jr. Memorial Library of Social Work.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; Young, Margaret B.; Young, Whitney M.; United States--Social conditions.; African Americans--History.; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations.; Charities.; Children's literature.; Civil Rights.; Public welfare--Societies, etc.; Social problems.; Social service--Societies, etc.; Sociologists.; Sociology, Urban--Societies, etc.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least 2 business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
of Marcia Young Cantarella and Lauren Young Casteel Gift 1/6/2011
- Series I: Whitney M. Young, Jr. Files, 1921-2009
  - Personal papers, 1921-1971 (Includes birth certificate, military discharge documents, death certificate, press clippings) (Box 1)
  - Professional papers
    - White House events, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
    - General, 1965-1970 (Box 1)
  - Writings, speeches, and publications, 1963-2003 (Box 1)
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Whitney M. Young, Jr. Memorial Library-Lagos, Nigeria, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Whitney M. Young, Jr. Memorial Foundation, Inc.-Dissolution, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - National Urban League, 1980-2010, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - National Urban League Conference tapes, 2004, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Clark Atlanta Graduate School of Social Work, 1971-2000 (Box 2)
  - Kentucky State University, 1977-1998 (Box 2)
  - Lincoln Foundation, 1979-1992 (Includes some correspondence with Margaret Young) (Box 2)
  - United States Postal Service, 1981-1998 (Box 2)
  - Columbia University, 1982-1998 (Box 2)
  - The Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania
    - Whitney M. Young, Jr. Professorship, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Whitney M. Young, Jr. Memorial Conference, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Dennis Dickerson-Whitney M. Young, Jr. Biography
    - Correspondence with Margaret Young regarding biography, 1992-1999 (Box 2)
    - Chapters 10 & 11 with Margaret Young annotations, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Whitney M. Young, Jr. commemoration-General, 1971-2009, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Pins
    - Nixon/Agnew Inaugural ca. 1969 (Box 7)
    - Kennedy for Equality ca. 1960 (Box 7)
  - Drawing of Chair (Box 7)
  - United States Postal Service-Whitney M. Young, Jr. Black Heritage stamp first day of issue covers, 1981 (Box 7)
  - Records
    - The Stars Salute Dr. Martin Luther King, ca. 1968 (Box 7)
    - In Memoriam Whitney Moore Young, Jr. 1921-1971 1971 (Box 7)
- Series II: Professional Activities, 1964-1996
  - White House events, 1964-1990 (Box 2)
  - Visit to Lagos, Nigeria, 1974 (Box 2)
  - United Nations
    - Decade for Action to Combat Racism and Seminar on Human Rights-Yugoslavia & Eastern Europe, 1973-1975, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - National Policy Panel to Study U.S.-China Relations-East Asia travel, 1978-1979, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Jimmy Carter-State visit to Brazil, Liberia, and Nigeria, 1978, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Philip Morris-Board of directors, 1972-1996 (Mainly regarding Berlin trip) (Box 3)
  - New York Life Insurance Company-Board of directors, 1980-1995 (Box 3)
- Series III: Writings and Publications, 1953-1997
  - “A Negro Mother Speaks of her Challenging Role in a Changing World”-Parents’ Magazine, 1964 (Box 3)
  - “How to Raise a Child Without Prejudice”-Public Affairs Pamphlet,1965-1977 (Box 3)
  - The First Book of American Negroes & The Picture Life of Martin Luther King, Jr., 1966-1967 (cover only) (Box 3)
  - Franklin Watts, Inc. Publishers, 1966-1984 (Includes press clippings, royalties, contracts) (Box 3)
  - Writings-General, ca. 1953-1997 (Includes articles, speeches, poetry, essays, and notes; 2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Institute of Children’s Literature-Correspondence course, 1982-1995, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Notes for a children’s story, ca. 1990s (Box 4)
- Series IV: Correspondence, 1945-2009
  - Letters from students
    - Books & classroom visits, 1967-1979 (Box 4)
    - Condolence, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Professional
    - Regarding books & articles, 1964-1971 (Box 4)
    - United Nations-Mainly regarding trip to Yugoslavia, 1974-1979 (Box 4)
    - United States Military Academy Board of Visitors, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
    - Dissolution of the Whitney M. Young, Jr. Memorial Foundation, 1990-1992 (Box 4)
    - General, 1958-2004 (Includes professional activity at New York Life, Philip Morris, Spelman College; 4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Personal
    - White House and big names, 1945-2001 (Includes a photocopied letter written by Whitney Young during World War II) (Box 5)
    - General, 1959-2005, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - Greeting cards, ca. 1970-2009 (Box 5)
  - Birthday greeting, 1972 (oversized; signed by Nelson Rockefeller, Spiro Agnew, James L. Buckley, and Terence Cardinal Cooke) (Box 9)
  - Letter from Lyndon B. Johnson, 1972 (oversized; concerns Civil Rights Symposium) (Box 9)
  - Letter from Jackie Kennedy Onassis, 1968 (oversized) (Box 9)
- Series V: Personal Papers, 1921-2010
  - General, 1921-1993 (Includes birth certificates, transcripts, passports) (Box 5)
  - Biographical information
    - Columbia University oral history, 1975-1984 (Three copies including a copy of the original transcript with annotations; 3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Who’s Who biographies and transcript of an interview with Chris Wilkins, 1989-1997 (Box 5)
  - Address books & planners, 1994-2000, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Newspaper clippings and articles, 1974-2003 (Includes writings by and about family members) (Box 5)
  - Obituaries & commemoration, 2009-2010 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1962-1965 (Mainly items related to Lyndon B. Johnson’s inauguration) (Box 9)
- Series VI: Photographs, 1930s-2003
  - Subseries VI.1: Margaret Young Photographs, 1930s-2003
    - Family and friends, ca. 1930s-2000 (Includes some childhood photos; 3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Headshots, ca. 1974-1991 (Includes some related correspondence) (Box 6)
    - Lagos, Nigeria, 1974 (Includes newspaper clippings) (Box 6)
    - United Nations
      - Poland & Yugoslavia, 1974 (Box 6)
      - China album, 1979 (Includes newspaper clippings) (Box 6)
    - Professional activities and events, ca. 1963-2003, (4 folders) (Box 10)
    - Souvenir photograph plate-Rio de Janeiro, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Philip Morris Nigeria album, 1974 (album and folder of loose photos) (Box 10)
    - Headshots and professional activities, ca. 1970s (oversized) (Box 10)
    - China trip, ca. 1978-1979 (oversized) (Box 10)
    - Nigeria, Ghana, and Spain album, 1974 (Box 11)
    - Philip Morris Board of Directors Meeting album-Berlin, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Subseries VI.2: Whitney M. Young, Jr. Photographs, 1943-1996
    - Family and friends, ca. 1943-1971 (Box 6)
    - Headshots, ca. 1960s (Box 6)
    - Professional activities and events, ca. 1962-1971 (Box 6)
    - Lagos, Nigeria, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Commemoration, ca. 1974-1998 (Box 6)
    - The Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania album-Whitney M. Young, Jr. Professorship, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Professional activities and events-White House and Lyndon B. Johnson, 1967 (oversized, includes attached correspondence) (Box 8)
    - Photo with children, ca. 1960-1971 (oversized) (Box 8)
    - Headshots, ca. 1960-1971 (oversized) (Box 8)
    - Photo with Pope Paul VI, 1970 (oversized) (Box 8)
    - Photo with Martin Luther King, Jr., ca. 1963 (oversized) (Box 8)
- Series VII: Awards and Recognition, 1971-1993
  - New York Service Award-John V. Lindsay, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Whitney M. Young, Jr.-Family of Man Award, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Urban League of Metropolitan Denver-McKinley Harris Distinguished Warrior Award, 2000 (Box 9)
  - Letter of recognition from the YWCA Salute to Women in Business, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Letter of recognition upon retirement from the Board of Directors of New York Life, 1992 (Box 9)
  - Letter of recognition from the Board of Directors of Altria Group, Inc, 2010 (Box 9)
  - Letter of recognition from the Board of Directors of New York Life, 2009 (Box 9)
  - Los Angeles Urban League medal, 1991 (Box 10)
  - Lady Bird Johnson-Recognition for Lyndon B. Johnson Civil Rights Symposium, 1972 (Box 12)
  - Philip Morris Minority Advisory Committee Plaque, 1993 (Box 12)
  - United States Military Academy Board of Visitors Plaque, ca. 1978-1981 (Box 12)
  - Dollars & Sense Top 100 Black Business and Professional Women Plaque (Box 12)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Annual Drum Major Memorial Award-New Rochelle Community Action Agency, 1979 (Box 12)